Hello everyone and welcome to
English Pod, my name is Markle.
My name is Catherine and today we
have a very complicated topic for you.
That's right this is
an upper intermediate
lesson a little bit
more difficult and we're
talking all about taxes,
paychecks and all the
information for when you
work in the United States.
That's right, it confuses
me and I'm American
so take a close listen
we're going to listen
to this dialogue one time and we'll be back
in a moment to discuss what's going on.
Hey Susan have you got a sec I have
some questions about my paycheck.
You better my name.
Pull up a chair.
Well this is my first
paycheck here in the States
and there are a few
things I don't understand.
First off what does this beaker and SUI SDI
tax and why are there deductions both for
the Medicare and for
my health insurance plan?
Okay let's start from
the top of your pay stop.
This number here represents your gross pay.
Yes that's easy enough to understand.
Then here we have a series of deductions.
First off are the federal
ones, FICA stands for Federal
Insurance Contribution
Act or something like that.
It's your federal income
tax and then there's
Social Security and
Medicare which are both
federal programs to help you out after
you retire or if you are unable to work.
All right I see so the Medicare isn't
actually a health insurance I can use now.
That's right.
Below the federal deductions
are the state deductions.
There's the state income tax and then this
SUISDI tax you were asking about is paying
into an unemployment and or
disability fund that our state has set up.
But you can see that it's a pretty
small quantity that they take.
Yeah I don't mind giving
them a dollar fifty for that.
So there are two
separate income taxes, one
at a state level and
one at a federal level.
That's right.
Not all states have income tax.
Some use higher property
taxes or sales taxes instead.
I see.
All right well I think everything
else I can figure out on my own.
The deductions for health insurance
and my 401k are pretty self-explanatory.
Thanks to the help season.
No problem.
All those deductions do add up and
nobody's not pay as high as they'd like.
I can understand why
you'd want some explanation.
Yeah I guess it's the same in the UK.
I just never paid much attention.
See you later.
All right we're back so
obviously a lot of vocab there.
A lot of acronyms as well
like FICA and all that stuff.
We'll take a look at
that in a little bit first.
Let's start off with some
language on language takeaway.
So when you get paid
there's a very important
number you want to look
at or a couple of numbers.
These are called deductions.
Now why do deductions
make people sad Marco?
Because a deduction is
to take away or reduce.
So obviously if your salary is let's say a
thousand dollars and you have five hundred
dollars deductions then you only
get five instead of a thousand dollars.
All right so deductions mean what
money is being taken away from you.
All right that's the money that's deducted
for certain taxes or certain programs.
It's important to
remember that deduct to
deduct is the opposite of
to add it means to take away.
To take away that's right.
So Emily had some
questions about her salary
and so she brought
her pay stub to Susan
to ask her why are all these deductions
well why am I not getting all my salary?
That's right so pay stubs are very important
pieces of paper basically when you go
to a store and you buy
something you get a receipt.
Well when you go to work and you get
paid you get a receipt for your payment.
That means that it shows you how much
money you earn and all of these deductions.
So if you if you're paid every month
you get a paid stub every month.
If you paid every two weeks you
get a paid stub every two weeks.
Okay so it's basically
a little receipt that
tells you you have been paid
and how much you were paid.
That's right.
All right so Susan started explaining
about her gross salary and her net salary.
All right and these are the two most
important numbers on your pay stub.
On your pay stub it will say gross pay
not gross like icky gross but like total.
So in total you earn
$1,000 a month but that's
not how much money
you have in your bank.
Because the money
that you earn is actually a
little bit different because of
these deductions we mentioned.
The net pay is the actual
amount of money you get to keep.
So the company will pay $1,000
but with taxes and all
these deductions the
actual money that you get is
less and that's called the net pay.
So it's important
when you're looking at
these numbers look
at your gross pay is that
correct and then
afterwards look at your net
pay is that what money
you actually received.
That's right.
All right so now
getting into a little bit
of taxes and this type
of taxes that we have
out there not considering
the taxes for the salary.
This is a different one.
We have a property tax.
That's right.
So some places in
America tax you on the
amounts of money you
earn at your job but a lot
of others like to collect
taxes from different areas.
So property tax is one of those.
If you own land, if
you own a house or a
condo, you will pay a
property tax every year.
Every year you have to
pay for owning this property.
That's right because
basically you're paying
the state for the land that you
have or the space that you have.
And the bigger your house is, the
bigger the land is, the more money you pay.
And you have to pay the same value
every year or does it change over time?
If you can change over
time, you hear that sometimes
property taxes are
property value increases
and so then property tax
will probably increase as well.
Okay.
And what about sales tax?
I think this is a very straightforward
but how does it work?
Well it's straightforward
Marco but I don't
think they have this in many
other places in the world.
It's kind of for example
we don't really have
a sales tax so people
don't have to worry about it.
But a sales tax is a small tax that
you pay every time you buy something.
Right.
So if I buy a TV and a TV is $100 it's
possible that the sales tax is 3% I pay $103.
So that's another way
that you are taxed not
on how much money you make
but on the purchases that you make.
It makes sense.
If I buy a lot of cool
things, cars, TVs,
I'm paying more money
to my state to provide
services like schools and
roads and things like that.
Okay.
So a lot of interesting things here I think
we can move on now to specifically talking
about the taxes related to people's salaries
or how it works in the United States.
This is a remember that we are talking
specifically about the United States here.
So let's take a look at that
now on Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder.
All right.
So one of the scary
acronyms here Marco was FICA.
FICA, it looks very strange
here what is this FICA?
Well, this is an acronym and remember
acronyms are words that stand for other words.
So F, Federal, I,
Insurance, C, Contribution
and A, Act, so Federal
Insurance, Contribution Act.
Basically this is a federal tax.
That means that it's
everyone in the country.
Everyone has to pay.
No matter where you live.
Yeah, Illinois, New York, California,
everyone has to pay and how much is this tax?
Do you know?
I do not know.
It's called a graduated income tax.
That means that people
who earn very little pay
very little, people who
earn a lot pay more.
Uh huh.
Okay.
So this is something
that everyone has to pay
and that's why it's
called federal tax, right?
That's right.
So in America, federal means national and
state means more local for your own state.
Okay.
Now, uh, she is obviously
paying the federal
tax that everyone has to
pay and what about Medicare?
All right.
So this is not a tax per se.
This is actually a
deduction that goes into,
um, kind of a fund, you
know, it's a government
program and that
when you're older, when
you're retired, uh,
you will receive benefits
from the federal government from the United
States government to get health care.
So Medicare is a kind of healthcare
that is paid for by the US government.
I see.
So when you're older, you don't really have
to pay for your hospital bills then because
you worked and contributed to this Medicare
fund, then you can go and get treatment.
That's right.
Or you pay for part of it
and they pay for part of it.
So it depends on the,
um, the system, but yes, it's
a way to get health care
through the government.
Okay.
And now our next word
is interesting because
we've heard about
social security before.
You have the social security card, which is
basically your ID or its state's also that
you are in American,
but what is the social
security fund now that
you are contributing to?
Well, basically, this is
another government
program that is designed
to make sure that people
are comfortable when they
stop working because when
you stop working, you don't
have any income anymore.
You need money to live.
And so your whole life, you, you're paying
into this fund and the government will then
give you the money
back some money to, uh,
to basically live off
of when you're retired.
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
And, uh, so how long
do you actually have to
work, uh, in order to be
eligible for social security?
I believe you have to be 65 to be eligible
for social security, but I'm not sure.
Is either 60 or 65.
Okay.
I'm not there yet.
All right.
And actually another
one that's very similar
is you have this 401k,
which is actually, uh,
a very interesting name
of, uh, for this tax or fund.
Yeah, 401k is more of an investment.
So a 401k is something
that you put money into
every month or year to, um, to
access later on when you're retired.
So again, it's, so it's a
kind of security for you.
If you work every day,
every year for 30 years,
40 years, you want to have some
money when you're when you're all done.
Right.
And this is basically a
retirement savings plan.
So, uh, what is the
difference between social
security and the 401k
or are they the same?
I think the difference is
the way the money goes.
I'm not 100%.
But all of these are like, you have to give
the government this money or can I say,
hey, hey, I don't want
to don't worry about me.
I don't need social security.
I'm set.
I'm saving all on my own.
And can I refuse to pay these
taxes for a one, K. Yes, you can refuse.
It's not a tax.
It's just something
that you can, uh, usually
this is not a government, this
is not a government program.
This is something that the company
that you work for will set up for you.
Okay.
But Medicare and social security,
these are things that you have to pay into.
Because even if you're
rich and you have all
this money, um, you
know, there are a lot
of people in America that don't have any of
this and so we consider it something that
we do for each other as
much as our for ourselves.
Uh huh.
Because also, you know,
Medicare and Medicaid,
these are programs that
you can also be eligible for.
Even if you're 25 years
old or 30 years old,
you use your poor,
you don't have a job.
So these are social programs.
Okay.
Very good.
It's very, very interesting.
You see that, uh, obviously this is why in
movies, uh, you see that people make fun
of taxes and how much tax in America
there is and, uh, how you can escape taxes.
But it's interesting to
see how it's made up and
why you are giving your
money to the government.
That's right.
So let's listen to today's dialogue again.
It was pretty complicated.
So hopefully you've understood a little
bit more after we've talked about it now.
Hey, Susan, have you got sick?
I have some questions about my paycheck.
You bet, Emily.
Pull up a chair.
Well, this is my first
paycheck here in the States
and there are a few
things I don't understand.
First off, what is this?
Speaker and SUI SDI
tax and why are there
deductions both for Medicare
and for my health insurance plan?
Okay.
Let's start from the top of your pay stop.
This number here
represents your growth pay.
Yes, that's easy enough to understand.
Then here we have a series of deductions.
First off are the federal
ones, Fika stands for
Federal Insurance Contribution
Act or something like that.
It's your federal income
tax and then there's
Social Security and
Medicare, which are both
federal programs to help you out after
you retire or if you are unable to work.
All right.
I see.
So the Medicare isn't actually a
health insurance I can use now.
That's right.
Below the federal deductions
are the state deductions.
There's the state income tax and then this
SUISDI tax you were asking about is paying
into an unemployment and or
disability fund that our state has set up.
But you can see that it's a pretty
small quantity that they take.
Yeah, I don't mind giving
them a dollar fifty for that.
So there are two
separate income taxes, one
at a state level and
one at a federal level.
That's right.
But all states have an income tax.
Some use higher property
taxes or sales taxes instead.
I see.
All right.
Well, I think everything else
I can figure out on my own.
The deductions for health insurance
and my 401(k) are pretty self-explanatory.
Thanks to the help season.
No problem.
All those deductions do add up and
nobody's net pay as high as they'd like.
I can understand why
you'd want some explanation.
Yeah, I guess it's the same in the UK.
I just never paid much attention.
See you later.
All right, so another
interesting thought that
came up was well, where does the money
for government spending come from?
So because you have
all these taxes that are
for you basically have
property tax or maybe
does it come from
sales tax that maybe the
government can make roads
and parks and stuff like this?
Well, that's the thing.
Now, remember where earlier we
talked about federal and state taxes?
Well, if it's a state
tax like sales tax, in
America, I can pay
sales tax in California
but maybe in New
Mexico, there is no sales tax.
So this is state tax
and that means that the
state government can
use the money for state
projects, parks,
roads, things like that.
But then the federal insurance contribution
act, the fight of this federal tax, that
is something that's used for
our military or government.
You know, this pays the
paychecks of people in Congress, the
president, this is where all the
money to pay them comes from.
And so basically the
state taxes pay for state
benefits and programs and the federal
taxes pay for these nationwide programs.
So that's I think one
of the most interesting
things about this
topic is that the United
States is like 50 small countries that
kind of have their own little governments.
You know, they have
their own taxes and they
have their own rules
like in some states
you can start driving when
you're 16 in others when you're 15.
And so it's like all these little small
countries but at the same time you have this
one make a country
that has federal taxes and
federal insurance and
military and all this.
That's true.
And you know, it's
interesting, it's an
interesting fact about
American history that the
most conflict in our country has
really come down to these two groups.
One group believes that
the federal government,
so that's the national government
should have more power than the states.
And another group believes that
the states should have more power.
And that is a big
problem, you know, this
disagreement that
we've had in America that
goes back to 1776 and
the founding fathers.
And so I don't think it's something that is
fixed, you know, these things change, you
know, sometimes more
federal power sometimes
last but it's a very interesting
part of American history.
And also it would be
interesting to hear from
our users how it works over there because
I know that approximately a rough estimate
is that around 30 to 40% of
Americans' income goes to tax, right?
About that, yeah.
So almost half of your
money goes into taxes.
So I wonder how much
it is in other people's
countries, maybe they have
60% of taxes or maybe 10?
Maybe 10.
Yeah.
So let us know.
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
We hope to see you guys there.
I'll see you guys in the next one.